<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: wallst | Confessions of a Wall Street Programmer]]></title>
  <link href="http://btorpey.github.io/blog/categories/wallst/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://btorpey.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-12-17T14:03:03-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://btorpey.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Torpey]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Visualizing Latency]]></title>
    <link href="http://btorpey.github.io/blog/2014/05/16/visualizing-latency/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-16T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://btorpey.github.io/blog/2014/05/16/visualizing-latency</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/images/ping.png" width="320" height="240"> 

I'm a visual thinker (I think I may have [mentioned that before](http://btorpey.github.io/blog/2014/04/29/a-picture-is-worth-1k-words/) ),
so when I'm analyzing performance, latency, etc. I find it really helpful to be
able to visualize what is going on on the machine. 

As a result, I had gotten
reasonably good at using Excel to produce charts, which sometimes helped to correlate observed
behaviors like latency spikes with other events on the machine.

For a bunch of reasons I wanted to move away from Excel, though, and find
another tool that would give me the same or better functionality.

<!--more-->

For one thing, a little over a year ago I switched to a Mac as my main machine
after years of using Windows. There was a certain amount of adjustment, but for
the most part it's been smooth sailing. More than that, I was actually able to
recapture some of the fun and excitement I remember from my first Apple (an
Apple ][).

I also wanted something that would run on both the Mac and Linux, where I do
most of my testing. Last but not least, I wanted something that would be
scriptable so I could easily produce consistent charts for multiple test runs.

I looked briefly at R, but ditched it when it used up all the 8GB in my laptop,
plus the entire hard disk as swap, for a single dataset of 100,000 points.
Probably my bad, but I didn't have the patience to figure out what I might be
doing wrong.

At that point I turned to venerable (some would say crusty) gnuplot. It's a bit
long in the tooth, but I just wanted to plot latency over time, so how hard
could that be? Well, I guess it's pretty easy if you already know how, but
starting from scratch is another story.

Which brings me to my rant of the day, directed at techies in general, and to the
(us?) Linux/Unix techies in particular.

Short version: I don't want to learn gnuplot. I don't even want to *have
learned* gnuplot -- even if I could do that by just taking a pill. What I want
is to be able to produce decent-looking charts *without* knowing *anything*
about gnuplot.

To be fair, the gnuplot docs did have some examples -- more anyway than you
would find in a typical man page, although that's admittedly a low bar. And
while my google-fu is usually pretty good, I just couldn't find anything on the
intertubes that would work for me, so I had to learn *just a little* gnuplot.

> When all else fails, read the instructions.

It turns out that gnuplot works pretty well, and will probably work even better
once I learn (sigh) how to use it better.

But you don't have to learn diddly if you don't want to. [Here is the first](<https://github.com/btorpey/latency-utils.git>) in
what will hopefully be a series of recipes that you can use with little or no
modification.  Once you've downloaded the repo, enter the following at the command prompt:

`./tsd.sh ping.csv x11`

Which should result in something like this:

<img class="center" src="/images/gnuplot.png"> 

It's primitive, but that very primitiveness has its own appeal, especially for
those of us for whom "UI" means bash, vi or emacs.

A couple of points about the gnuplot command files:

-   Sometimes you care about the actual time that an event took place, so you
can correlate it with some other event; sometimes you don't. Accordingly, I've
created two different files: one which displays actual time (ts.gp), the other
which calculates and displays deltaT (tsd.gp).

-   I've been programming in C (and later C++) for many years, but I don't think
I've ever purposely used the comma operator before. Well, expressions in gnuplot
follow C language rules for operators, precedence, etc. and that comma operator
turns out to be handy -- in this case it lets us 
update the origin in the same expression that calculates deltaT.
(The return value of the comma
operator is the right-hand expression).

-- (Note that the above requires something like gnuplot 4.6)


-   I've left the default terminal in the gnuplot command files, but you can 
specify a different one on the command line.  To get a list of terminals supported 
in your version:
`gnuplot -e "set terminal"`.

Comments, suggestions, pull requests, etc. welcome.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What's Old Is New Again]]></title>
    <link href="http://btorpey.github.io/blog/2014/02/11/whats-old-is-new-again/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-11T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://btorpey.github.io/blog/2014/02/11/whats-old-is-new-again</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Sometimes it seems that all this low-latency, HFT stuff is new, but then
you see something like this…</p>

<!--more-->

<p><img class="center" src="http://edison.rutgers.edu/images/xx/xx1325.jpg"> </p>

<p>Source: The Thomas Edison Papers, Rutgers University <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p><a href="http://edison.rutgers.edu/NamesSearch/glocpage.php3?gloc=X135&amp;">http://edison.rutgers.edu/NamesSearch/glocpage.php3?gloc=X135&amp;</a><a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[FIXing less]]></title>
    <link href="http://btorpey.github.io/blog/2014/02/10/fixing-less/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://btorpey.github.io/blog/2014/02/10/fixing-less</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here's a handy tip for those who (like me) spend a fair amount of time staring
at FIX logs.

<!--more-->

FIX may be the protocol that everybody loves to hate, but it doesn't look like it's
going anywhere, so I guess we all just need to get over it and learn to live with it.

One of the things that is hard to live with, though -- at least for me -- is the
visual cacophony that results when browsing FIX logs with less.
<img class="center" src="/images/less-before.png"> 

It turns out that it's possible to control how less displays the x'01'
delimiters to make this chore a little easier on the eyes.  In my case, I
use the following in my .bash_profile:

`export LESSBINFMT="*u%x"`

This dials down the visual clutter to a level that I find much easier to deal
with.
<img class="center" src="/images/less-after.png"> 


(Note that the man page for less mentions that it's possible to display the hex codes in square brackets, but I have not found that to work on any of the systems where I've tried it -- YMMV).
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
