<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: bash | Confessions of a Wall Street Programmer]]></title>
  <link href="http://btorpey.github.io/blog/categories/bash/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://btorpey.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-12-17T14:14:13-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://btorpey.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Torpey]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Where Am I?]]></title>
    <link href="http://btorpey.github.io/blog/2014/05/29/where-am-i/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-29T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://btorpey.github.io/blog/2014/05/29/where-am-i</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="/images/gilligans-island-tv-show.jpg" width="320" height="240"> 

From *Robinson Crusoe* to *Gilligan's Island* to *Lost*, tales of being
stranded on a desert island seem to resonate with people in a special way. Some
of that likely has to do with the exotic locales, and the practical challenges
of getting water, food and shelter.

But an even more basic part is the unanswered question: "Where am I?" that makes
things so -- well, *mysterious*.

Shell scripting can be pretty mysterious too at times, but in this installment
we'll learn how to answer that basic question of "Where am I?" to make shell
scripting a little less mysterious.

<!--more-->

One of the tenets of the Unix way is brevity, and one consequence of that is
that well-behaved programs should be able to find whatever other resources they
need without having to be told where they are. Windows attempts to
solve this problem with the (gack!) registry, but Unix tends to use a simpler
approach: needed resources are placed either in well-known locations (e.g., /etc
for system programs), or where they can be found relative to the location of the
program itself.

Another attribute of a well-behaved Unix program is that it
should be able to run from any location, whether it's invoked with a full path,
or found via the PATH variable.

So, how do we reconcile those two requirements? And specifically, how do we do
that in shell scripts? Since -- regardless of what your "main" language is, if
you're programming in Unix/Linux, you're probably also writing a boatload of
shell scripts too.

It turns out that, at least in bash, there is a
simple but non-obvious way to do get the location of the script file itself,
which goes something like this:

    SCRIPT_DIR=$(cd $(dirname ${BASH_SOURCE}) && /bin/pwd) 

Let's follow this through and see how it works:

-   The `$( ... )` construct invokes a sub-shell. This is handy since it
allows us to change the environment of the sub-shell (e.g., current directory)
without affecting the current environment.

-   `$BASH_SOURCE` is a builtin variable that gives us the path to the shell
script itself. For instance, if we invoke a script with `./scriptname.sh`,
then that's what will end up in `${BASH_SOURCE}`.

-   To get the full path then we extract just the path part with `dirname`, again
in a sub-shell.

-   We then `cd` into that directory, and if successful get the full pathname
with `/bin/pwd`.
    -   Note that we use `/bin/pwd` to get the path. This version resolves any
    symbolic links to return the actual physical path. There is also a `pwd`
    built-in to bash, but that one does not expand symbolic links by default.
<br>
-   Finally, the result is assigned to SCRIPT_DIR.

We now have the full path of the script file itself, and can use that to locate
any other resources needed by the script. For a real-world example, you can
check out the [these scripts](<https://github.com/btorpey/latency-utils.git>) from
 [my earlier post on visualizing latency](</blog/2014/05/16/visualizing-latency/>).


</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
