<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: c++ | Confessions of a Wall Street Programmer]]></title>
  <link href="http://btorpey.github.io/blog/categories/c-plus-plus/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://btorpey.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-12-17T16:48:14-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://btorpey.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Torpey]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Even Mo' Static]]></title>
    <link href="http://btorpey.github.io/blog/2016/11/12/even-mo-static/"/>
    <updated>2016-11-12T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://btorpey.github.io/blog/2016/11/12/even-mo-static</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/images/vandergraaf.jpg" width="139" height="122">

- Will be replaced with the ToC, excluding the "Contents" header
{:toc}

A while back I wrote [an article](/blog/2016/04/07/mo-static/) that compared cppcheck and clang's static analyzers (clang-check and clang-tidy).  The folks who make [PVS-Studio](http://www.viva64.com/en/pvs-studio/) (the guys with the unicorn mascot that you've probably been seeing a lot of lately) saw the article, and suggested that I take a look at their Linux port, which was then in beta test, and write about it.

So I did.  Read on for an overview of PVS-Studio, and how it compared to [cppcheck](http://cppcheck.sourceforge.net/).

<!-- more -->

In [the earlier article](/blog/2016/04/07/mo-static/), I used a [benchmark suite](https://github.com/regehr/itc-benchmarks) developed by Toyota ITC, and written about by [John Regehr](http://blog.regehr.org/archives/1217), who is a professor of Computer Science at the University of Utah.  The ITC suite consists of code that is specially written to exhibit certain errors that can be detected by static analysis, so that the code can be used to evaluate the performance of different tools.

In this article, I am going to use the same test suite to compare PVS-Studio with cppcheck.  I'll also talk about my experience using both tools to analyze two relatively large real-world codebases that I help maintain as part of my day job.

## TL;DR
Using any static analysis tool is better than using none, and in general the more the merrier.  Each tool has its own design philosophy, and corresponding strengths and weaknesses.

Daniel Marjamäki[^daniel] and the maintainers of [cppcheck](http://cppcheck.sourceforge.net/) have done a terrific job creating a free tool that can go head-to-head with expensive commercial offerings.  You can't go wrong with cppcheck, either as a gentle introduction to static analysis, or as the one-and-only tool for the budget-conscious.  But don't take my word for it -- the Debian project uses cppcheck as part of its [Debian Automated Code Analysis](https://qa.debian.org/daca/) project to check over 100GB of C++ source code.

[^daniel]: Daniel was recently interviewed on [CppCast](http://cppcast.com/2016/11/daniel-marjamaki/). 

[PVS-Studio](http://www.viva64.com/en/pvs-studio/) is also a terrific tool, but it is definitely _not_ free.  (When a product [doesn't have published prices](http://www.viva64.com/en/order/), you know it's going to cost serious money).

Whether PVS-Studio is worth the price is a judgement call, but if it can find just one bug that would have triggered a crash in production it will have paid for itself many times over. 

And while PVS-Studio doesn't appear to have been adopted by a high-profile project like Debian, the folks who make it are certainly not shy about running various open-source projects through their tool and [reporting the results](http://www.viva64.com/en/inspections/).  

So, if your budget can handle it, use both.  If money is a concern, then you may want to start out with cppcheck and use that to help build a case for spending the additional coin that it will take to include commercial tools like PVS-Studio in your toolbox.

Note also that PVS-Studio offers a trial version, so you can give it a go on your own code, which is, after all, the best way to see what the tool can do.  And, if you use the provided [helper scripts](/pages/REAME.md/index.html) ([repo here](https://github.com/btorpey/static)), your results will be in a format that makes it easy to compare the tools.

## Methodology
In comparing cppcheck and PVS-Studio, I used the ITC test suite that I wrote about in an [earlier article](/blog/2016/04/07/mo-static/).  I also used both tools to analyze real-world code bases which I deal with on a day-to-day basis and that I am intimately familiar with.

### ITC test suite
The ITC test suite that I've been using to compare static analyzers is intended to provide a common set of source files that can be used as input to various static analysis tools.  It includes both real errors, as well as "false positives" intended to trick the tools into flagging legitimate code as an error.

So far, so good, and it's certainly very helpful to know where the errors are (and are not) when evaluating a static analysis tool.  

#### Caveats
In my email discussion with Andrey Karpov of PVS, he made the point that not all bugs are equal, and that a "checklist" approach to comparing static analyzers may not be the best.  I agree, but being able to compare analyzers on the same code-base can be very helpful, not least for getting a feel for how the tools work.

Your mileage can, and will, vary, so it makes sense to get comfortable with different tools and learn what each does best.  And there's no substitute for running the tools on your own code.  (The [helper scripts](/pages/REAME.md/index.html) ([repo here](https://github.com/btorpey/static)) may, well, help).

##### Specific issues 
The ITC test suite includes some tests for certain categories of errors that are more likely to manifest themselves at run-time, as opposed to compile-time.    

For instance, the ITC suite includes a relatively large number of test cases designed to expose memory-related problems.  These include problems like leaks, double-free's, dangling pointers, etc.

That's all very nice, but in the real world memory errors are often not that clear-cut, and depend on the dynamic behavior of the program at run-time.  Both valgrind's [memcheck](http://valgrind.org/info/tools.html#memcheck) and clang's [Address Sanitizer](http://clang.llvm.org/docs/AddressSanitizer.html) do an excellent job of detecting memory errors at run-time, and I use both regularly.

But run-time analyzers can only analyze code that actually runs, and memory errors can hide for quite a long time in code that is rarely executed (e.g., error & exception handlers). So, even though not all memory errors can be caught at compile-time, the ability to detect at least some of them can very helpful.  

A similar situation exists with regard to concurrency (threading) errors -- though in this case neither tool detects *any* of the concurrency-related errors seeded in the ITC code.  This is, I think, a reasonable design decision  -- the subset of threading errors that can be detected at compile-time is so small that it's not really worth doing (and could give users of the tool a false sense of security).  For concurrency errors, you again will probably be better off with something like clang's [Thread Sanitizer](http://clang.llvm.org/docs/ThreadSanitizer.html) or valgrind's [Data Race Detector](http://valgrind.org/info/tools.html#drd).

Also, in the interest of full disclosure, I have spot-checked some of the ITC code, but by no means all, to assure myself that its diagnostics were reasonable. 

With those caveats out of the way, though, the ITC test suite does provide at least a good starting point towards a comprehensive set of test cases that can be used to exercise different static analyzers.

## Real-world test results
I also ran both cppcheck and PVS-Studio on the code bases that I maintain as part of my day job, to get an idea of how the tools compare in more of a real-world situation.  While I can't share the detailed comparisons, following are some of the major points.

For the most part, both cppcheck and PVS-Studio reported similar warnings on the same code, with a few exceptions (listed following). 

cppcheck arguably does a better job of flagging "style" issues -- and while some of these warnings are perhaps a bit nit-picky, many are not:

- one-argument ctor's not marked `explicit` 
- functions that can/should be declared `static` or `const`
- use of post-increment on non-primitive types 
- use of obsolete or deprecated functions
- use of C-style casts

PVS-Studio, on the other hand, appears to include more checks for issues that aren't necessarily problems with the use of C++ per se, but things that would be a bug, or at least a "code smell", in any language.

A good example of that is PVS-Studio's warning on similar or identical code sequences (potentially indicating use of the copy-paste anti-pattern -- I've written about that [before](/blog/2014/09/21/repent/)).

Some other PVS-Studio "exclusives" include: 

- classes that define a copy ctor without `operator=`, and vice-versa
- potential floating-point problems[^float], e.g., comparing floating-point values for an exact match using `==`
- empty `catch` clauses
- catching exceptions by value rather than by reference

Both tools did a good job of identifying potentially suspect code, as well as areas where the code could be improved.

[^float]: See [here](http://blog.reverberate.org/2014/09/what-every-computer-programmer-should.html) and [here](http://floating-point-gui.de/) for an explanation of how floating-point arithmetic can produce unexpected results if you're not careful.

## False positives
False positives (warnings on code that is actually correct) are not really a problem with either cppcheck or PVS-Studio.  The few warnings that could be classified as false positives indicate code that is at the very least suspect -- in most cases you're going to want to change the code anyway, if only to make it clearer.

If you still get more false positives than you can comfortably deal with, or if you want to stick with a particular construct even though it may be suspect, both tools have mechanisms to suppress individual warnings, or whole classes of errors.  Both tools are also able to silence warnings either globally, or down to the individual line of code, based on inline comments.

## Conclusion
If you care about building robust, reliable code in C++ then you would be well-rewarded to include static analysis as part of your development work-flow.  

Both [PVS-Studio](http://www.viva64.com/en/pvs-studio/) and [cppcheck](http://cppcheck.sourceforge.net/) do an excellent job of identifying potential problems in your code.  It's almost like having another set of eyeballs to do code review, but with the patience to trace through all the possible control paths, and with a voluminous knowledge of the language, particularly the edge cases and "tricky bits".

Having said that, I want to be clear that static analysis is not a substitute for the dynamic analsyis provided by tools like valgrind's [memcheck](http://valgrind.org/info/tools.html#memcheck) and [Data Race Detector](http://valgrind.org/info/tools.html#drd), or clang's [Address Sanitizer](http://clang.llvm.org/docs/AddressSanitizer.html) and [Thread Sanitizer](http://clang.llvm.org/docs/ThreadSanitizer.html).  You'll want to use them too, as there are certain classes of bugs that can only be detected at run-time.

I hope you've found this information helpful.  If you have, you may want to check out some of my earlier articles, including:

- [Mo' Static](/blog/2016/04/07/mo-static/)
- [Static Analysis with clang](/blog/2015/04/27/static-analysis-with-clang/)
- [Using clang's Address Sanitizer](/blog/2014/03/27/using-clangs-address-sanitizer/)
- [Who Knows what Evil Lurks...](/blog/2015/03/17/shadow/)

Last but not least, please feel free to [contact me](<mailto:wallstprog@gmail.com>) directly, or post a comment below, if you have questions or something to add to the discussion.

## Appendix: Helper scripts and sample results

I've posted the [helper scripts](/pages/REAME.md/index.html) I used to run PVS-Studio, as well as the results of running those scripts on the ITC code, in the [repo](https://github.com/btorpey/static).

## Appendix: Detailed test results

The following sections describe a subset of the tests in the ITC code and how both tools respond to them.

### Bit Shift errors
{:.no_toc}
For the most part, PVS-Studio and cpphceck both do a good job of detecting errors related to bit shifts. Neither tool detects all the errors seeded in the benchmark code, although they miss different errors.

### Buffer overrun/underrun errors
{:.no_toc}
cppcheck appears to do a more complete job than PVS-Studio of detecting buffer overrrun and underrun errors, although it is sometimes a bit "off" -- reporting errors on lines that are in the vicinity of the actual error, rather than on the actual line.  cppcheck also reports calls to functions that generate buffer errors, which is arguably redundant, but does no harm.

PVS-Studio catches some of the seeded errors, but misses several that cppcheck detects.

While not stricly speaking an overrun error, cppcheck can also detect some errors where code overwrites the last byte in a null-terminated string.

### Conflicting/redundant conditions
{:.no_toc}
Both cppcheck and PVS-Studio do a good job of detecting conditionals that always evaluate to either true or false, with PVS-Studio being a bit better at detecting complicated conditions composed of contstants.

On the other hand, cppcheck flags redundant conditions (e.g., `if (i<5 && i<10)`), which PVS-Studio doesn't do. 

### Loss of integer precision
{:.no_toc}
Surprisingly, neither tool does a particularly good job of detecting loss of integer precision (the proverbial "ten pounds of bologna in a five-pound sack" problem ;-)

#### Assignments
{:.no_toc}
I say surprisingly because these kinds of errors would seem to be relatively easy to detect.  Where both tools seem to fall short is to assume that just because a value fits in the target data type, the assignment is valid -- but they fail to take into account that such an assignment can lose precision.

I wanted to convince myself that the ITC code was correct, so I pasted some of the code into a small test program:

<div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'><figcaption><span> (test1.c)</span> <a href='/downloads/code/static/pvs/test1.c'>download</a></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
<span class='line-number'>18</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='c'><span class='line'><span class="cp">#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="kt">int</span> <span class="n">sink</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="kt">void</span> <span class="nf">data_lost_001</span> <span class="p">()</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>	<span class="kt">char</span> <span class="n">ret</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>	<span class="kt">short</span> <span class="n">a</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mh">0x80</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>	<span class="n">ret</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">a</span><span class="p">;</span><span class="cm">/*Tool should detect this line as error*/</span> <span class="cm">/*ERROR:Integer precision lost because of cast*/</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="n">sink</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">ret</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="kt">int</span> <span class="nf">main</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="kt">int</span> <span class="n">argc</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="kt">char</span><span class="o">**</span> <span class="n">argv</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="n">printf</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">&quot;Value of sink=%d</span><span class="se">\n</span><span class="s">&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">sink</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">}</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></notextile></div>

When you run this program, you'll get the following output:

    $ gcc test1.c && ./a.out
    Value of sink=0

What is happening here is that the value 0x80 would fit in an *unsigned* char, but because the high-order bit is dedicated to the sign bit, the maximum value that can be represented in a signed char is 127.  So, the result of the assignment is zero, which is very likely not what would have been intended by the programmer.

#### Arithmetic expressions
{:.no_toc}
cppcheck does do a slightly better job of detecting integer overflow and underflow in arithmetic expressions compared to PVS, but still misses a number of seeded errors.

#### Divide by zero
{:.no_toc}
Both PVS-Studio and cppcheck do a good job of catching potential divide-by-zero errors, with cppcheck having a slight edge. 

### Dead code
{:.no_toc}
PVS-Studio tends to do a somewhat better job than cppcheck at detecting various types of dead code, such as `for` loops and `if` statements where the condition will never be true.

PVS-Studio also very helpfully flags any unconditional `break` statements in a loop -- these are almost always going to be a mistake.

### Concurrency
{:.no_toc}
As mentioned above, neither tool detects *any* of the concurrency-related errors seeded in the ITC code.  Again, I regard that as a reasonable design choice, given the relatively small percentage of such errors that can be detected at compile-time.

### Memory Errors
{:.no_toc}
As discussed earlier, not all memory errors can be detected at compile-time, so the lack of any error output certainly doesn't mean that the code doesn't have memory errors -- it just means that they can't be detected by the tools. But while may memory errors cannot be detected at compile-time, for those that can be, detecting them is a big win.

#### Double free
{:.no_toc}
cppcheck does an excellent job of detecting double-free errors (11 out of 12), while PVS-Studio only flags one of the seeded errors.

#### Free-ing non-allocated memory
{:.no_toc}
On the other hand, PVS-Studio does a better job of detecting attempts to free memory that was not allocated dynamically (e.g., local variables).  

#### Freeing a NULL pointer
{:.no_toc}
Neither tool does a particularly good job of catching these.  Perhaps that is because freeing a NULL pointer is actually not an error, but doing so is certainly a clue that the code may have other problems.

#### Dangling pointers
{:.no_toc}
cppcheck does a somewhat better job of detecting the use of dangling pointers (where the pointed-to object has already been freed).

#### Allocation failures
{:.no_toc}
If you're writing code for an embedded system, then checking for and handling allocation failures can be important, because your application is likely written to expect them, and do something about them.  But more commonly, running out of memory simply means that you're screwed, and attempting to deal with the problem is unlikely to make things better.

Neither tool detects code that doesn't handle allocation failures, but cppcheck does flag some allocation-related problems (as leaks, which is not correct, but it is a clue that there is a problem lurking).

#### Memory Leaks
{:.no_toc}
Typically, memory leaks are only evident at run-time, but there are some cases where they can be detected at compile-time, and in those cases cppcheck does a pretty good job. 

#### Null pointer
{:.no_toc}
Both PVS-Studio and cppcheck do a good job of flagging code that dereferences a NULL pointer, although neither tool catches all the errors in the benchmark code.

#### Returning a pointer to a local variable
{:.no_toc}
Both PVS-Studio and cppcheck detect returning a pointer to a local variable that is allocated on the stack.

#### Accessing un-initialized memory
{:.no_toc}
PVS-Studio does a somewhat better job than cppcheck of flagging accesses to uninitialized memory.

### Infinite loops
{:.no_toc}
Both cppcheck and PVS-Studio detect some infinite loop errors, but miss several others.  It could be that this is by design, since the code that is not flagged tends to resemble some idioms (e.g., ` while (true)`) that are often used deliberately.  

### Ignored return values
{:.no_toc}
PVS-Studio is quite clever here -- it will complain about an unused return value from a function, *if* it can determine that the function has no side effects.  It also knows about some common STL functions that do not have side effects, and will warn if their return values are ignored.

cppcheck doesn't check for return values per se, but it will detect an assignment that is never referenced.  This makes some sense, since warning on ignored return values could result in a large number of false positives.

### Empty/short blocks
{:.no_toc}
Both tools detect certain cases of empty blocks (e.g., `if (...);` -- note the trailing semi-colon).  

What neither tool does is warn about "short" blocks -- where a conditional block is not enclosed in braces, and so it's not 100% clear whether the conditional is meant to cover more than one statement:


    if (...)
       statement1();
       statement2();

If you've adopted a convention that even single-statement blocks need to be enclosed in braces, then this situation may not pertain (and good for you!).  Still, I think this would be a worthwhile addition -- at least in the "style" category.

### Dead stores
{:.no_toc}
cppcheck does a particularly good job of detecting dead stores (where an assignment is never subsequently used).  PVS-Studio, on the other hand, flags two or more consecutive assignments to a variable, without an intervening reference.  PVS-Studio will also flag assignment of a variable to itself (which is unlikely to be what was intended).
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mo' Static]]></title>
    <link href="http://btorpey.github.io/blog/2016/04/07/mo-static/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-07T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://btorpey.github.io/blog/2016/04/07/mo-static</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/images/nye-static.jpg" width="240" height="180">

- Will be replaced with the ToC, excluding the "Contents" header
{:toc}

In my day job, one of my main focuses is software reliability and correctness, so it makes sense that I would be a big fan of static analysis.

I've written previously about the [static analysis provided by clang](/blog/2015/04/27/static-analysis-with-clang/).  Today, I want to take a bit of a "deep-dive" into the whole subject by putting both clang and [cppcheck](http://cppcheck.sourceforge.net/) through their paces, using them to analyze a benchmark suite designed to exercise static analysis tools.  In the course of doing that, I'll also provide some helper scripts that make working with the tools easier.  

<!-- more -->

## Testing Static Analysis Tools

>  And what is good Phaedrus, and what is not good -- need we ask anyone to tell us these things? [^zen]  

[^zen]: Robert Pirsig, "Zen and the Art of Motorcycle Maintenance"

Obviously, the ultimate goal is to be able to run static analysis tools against our own codebase(s) to help detect and fix problems.  But how do we know if a particular tool is actually finding problems?  And, how do we know if we're running the tool properly?  

The perfect static analyzer would find all the latent bugs in our code, while not reporting any false positives[^fpos].  Since there are no perfect analyzers, any tool we use is going to miss some errors, and/or wrongly flag correct code.  So, the only way to evaluate an analyzer is to know where all the bugs are in our code -- but if we knew that, we wouldn't need an analyzer.

[^fpos]: A "false positive" is when a tool reports an error that is actually not.

That's a dilemma. To resolve it, we're going to be using a codebase specifically designed to trigger static analysis warnings.  The code was originally developed by Toyota ITC, and is available on [John Regehr's excellent blog](http://blog.regehr.org/archives/1217).  

The ITC benchmarks attempt to resolve our dilemma by providing both a set of code that contains errors which *should* trigger warnings, as well as a second set of code, similar to the first, but which doesn't contain errors.  Each source file is annotated with comments documenting where the errors are (and aren't).  And that lets us create a catalog of both real errors and potential false positives[^disclaimer]. 

To get started, download the code from [its GitHub repository](https://github.com/regehr/itc-benchmarks), and set the `ITCBENCH_ROOT` environment variable (which will come in handy later):

    $ git clone https://github.com/regehr/itc-benchmarks
    $ export ITCBENCH_ROOT=$(pwd)/itc-benchmarks

## Can I haz teh codez?
The remainder of this article goes step-by-step through the process of creating a compilation database from the ITC benchmark code, running clang's static analysis tools against that compilation database, building and installing cppcheck and running it against the compilation database, and analyzing the results.

This is all good stuff, especially if you're going to be using these tools going forward.  But, there's a certain amount of unavoidable yak-shaving[^yak] going on to get to that point.  So if you prefer to skip all that, I've included the results of running the different tools in the samples directory of the [repo](https://github.com/btorpey/static).  The samples include all the files we're going to be generating the hard way, so you can follow along without all the requisite busy-work.  Hopefully, when we're done you'll want to go back and use these tools on your own codebase. 

[^yak]: See <https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/yak_shaving> for a description of this colorful term.

## Creating a compilation database
To run both clang and cppcheck we first need to create a "compilation database" to supply them with required build settings.  The [compilation database](http://clang.llvm.org/docs/JSONCompilationDatabase.html) format was developed as part of the clang project, to provide a way for different tools to query the actual options used to build each file.

A [good overview of how the compilation database works](http://eli.thegreenplace.net/2014/05/21/compilation-databases-for-clang-based-tools) with clang-based tools can be found at Eli Bendersky's excellent site.  His article illustrates the importance of making sure that code analysis tools are looking at the same (pre-processed) source that the actual compiler sees, in order to generate meaningful diagnostics with a minimum of false positives.

- If you are using [cmake](http://cmake.org/) to drive your builds, creating a compilation database couldn't be easier -- simply add the `-DCMAKE_EXPORT_COMPILE_COMMANDS=ON` parameter to the cmake build command, or add the following to your main CMakeLists.txt file:

    `set(CMAKE_EXPORT_COMPILE_COMMANDS ON)`

- If you're not using cmake, you can still create a compilation database using plain old make by front-ending make with [Bear](<https://github.com/rizsotto/Bear>)[^bear], like so:

    `bear make`

In either case, the end result should be the creation of a  `compile_commands.json` file in the current directory.

Sadly, the ITC benchmark suite is stuck in the past using [autotools](https://twitter.com/timmartin2/status/23365017839599616), and worse yet, a version that needs to be installed from source (on RH6, at least).     

So, in the interest of immediate gratification, I've included the compile\_commands.json file [here](/downloads/code/static/samples/compile_commands.json) -- simply save it to the directory where you've cloned the ITC code.  (The compile_commands.json file is also contained in the samples directory of the [repo for this article](https://github.com/btorpey/static)).

If you prefer to generate the compile_commands.json file yourself using Bear, you can do so like this:

    $ cd ${ITCBENCH_ROOT}  
    $ ./bootstrap
    $ ./configure
    $ bear make

[^bear]: Building and installing Bear from source is relatively straightforward -- just keep in mind that you need python >= 2.7.

## Establishing a baseline
To make it possible to compare results from different analyzers, we first need to establish a baseline using the ITC benchmarks, and for that we're going to need [this set of helper scripts](/pages/REAME.md/index.html), which can be downloaded from [this GitHub repo](https://github.com/btorpey/static).

    $ git clone https://github.com/btorpey/static
    
Once you've done that, you need to add the directory to your PATH:

    $ export PATH=$(pwd)/static/scripts:$PATH 

Enter the following command from the ITC source directory to create a csv file with the error annotations from the ITC code:

    $ cd ${ITCBENCH_ROOT}  
    $ cc_driver.pl -n grep -Hni ERROR: | 
    itc2csv.pl -r ${ITCBENCH_ROOT}/ | 
    sort -u > itc.csv  


The command will create a file named `itc.csv` in the source directory that looks like this:

    $ cat itc.csv
    "01.w_Defects/bit_shift.c:106","/*ERROR:Bit shift error*/"
    "01.w_Defects/bit_shift.c:120","/*ERROR:Bit shift error*/"
    "01.w_Defects/bit_shift.c:133","/*ERROR:Bit shift error*/"
    "01.w_Defects/bit_shift.c:146","/*ERROR:Bit shift error*/"
    "01.w_Defects/bit_shift.c:163","/*ERROR:Bit shift error*/"
    "01.w_Defects/bit_shift.c:175","/*ERROR:Bit shift error*/"
    ...

The format of the csv file is really simple -- just an entry for file and line number, and another with the error annotation munged from the source file.  This will give us a baseline against which to compare both clang and cppcheck.


## Using clang's analysis tools

In a couple of previous posts, I wrote about [static analysis with clang](/blog/2015/04/27/static-analysis-with-clang), and [how to build clang](/blog/2015/01/02/building-clang).  This next bit assumes that you've got clang ready-to-go, but if that's not the case, there can be a fair amount of work required to get to that point, so you may want to skip ahead to the section on [using cppcheck](#using-cppcheck).

We're going to use a similar approach to the one we used above to generate the list of expected errors from the ITC code.  The command below will run clang-check against all the files in compile_commands.json, filter the results, and reformat the output in csv format:

    $ cd ${ITCBENCH_ROOT}  
    $ cc_driver.pl clang-check -analyze 2>&1 | 
    clang2csv.pl -r ${ITCBENCH_ROOT}/ |
    sort -u > clangcheck.csv

This gives us the diagnostic messages produced by clang, in the same csv format as we used for the list of errors, above: 

    $ cat clangcheck.csv
    "01.w_Defects/bit_shift.c:106","warning: The result of the '<<' expression is undefined"
    "01.w_Defects/bit_shift.c:133","warning: The result of the '<<' expression is undefined"
    "01.w_Defects/bit_shift.c:146","warning: The result of the '<<' expression is undefined"
    "01.w_Defects/bit_shift.c:163","warning: The result of the '<<' expression is undefined"
    "01.w_Defects/bit_shift.c:175","warning: The result of the '<<' expression is undefined"
    ...

We can already see that there are some differences: the ITC code expects to see a diagnostic at 01.w_Defects/bit_shift.c:120, but clang doesn't output a warning for that line.

### Analyzing the results

What I like to do at this point is fire up my all-time favorite tool, [Beyond Compare](/blog/2013/01/29/beyond-compare/), to generate a visual diff of the two files:

<img class="center" src="/images/itcvsclang.png"> 

This view shows the expected diagnostics extracted from the ITC source files on the left, alongside the diagnostics generated by clang on the right.  We can see that clang catches some of the bugs in the source file, but misses others.  If we continue to read down the two files, we'll also see some potential "false positives" -- i.e., diagnostics issued by clang that are not marked as expected errors in the source files. 

The visual approach using Beyond Compare works well for me, but with a csv-formatted datafile, other approaches are possible as well.  We could import the diagnostic messages into a spreadsheet program, or even a DBMS, for archiving, tracking and comparison. 

## Running clang analysis (again)
clang actually has two tools for doing static analysis -- in the example above we ran `clang-check -analyze`, but now we're going to use `clang-tidy` instead.

    $ cd ${ITCBENCH_ROOT}  
    $ cc_driver.pl clang-tidy 2>&1 | 
    clang2csv.pl -r ${ITCBENCH_ROOT}/ | 
    sort -u > clangtidy.csv

If you compare the results from clang-check and clang-tidy, you'll notice that clang-tidy generally reports more warnings than clang-check.  Some of them are not necessarily defects, but are arguably bad practice (e.g., using `strcpy`).

<img class="center" src="/images/clangcheckvstidy.png"> 

clang-tidy also outputs a slightly different format, including the name of the check in brackets.  (The name can also be used to suppress the warning).

The choice of which to use is up to you -- my preference is to use clang-check first, and follow up with clang-tidy, simply because the warnings produced by clang-tidy either duplicate those from clang-check, or are not as serious.

Note that you can get a list of available checks from clang with the following command:

    $ clang -cc1 -analyzer-checker-help
    ...
    core.DivideZero                 Check for division by zero
    core.DynamicTypePropagation     Generate dynamic type information
    core.NonNullParamChecker        Check for null pointers passed as arguments to a function whose arguments are references or marked with the 'nonnull' attribute
    core.NullDereference            Check for dereferences of null pointers
    core.StackAddressEscape         Check that addresses to stack memory do not escape the function


## Using cppcheck

There's another static analysis tool that can provide results comparable to clang.  [cppcheck](http://cppcheck.sourceforge.net/) has been around for a while, and I had tried to get it working in the past, but had given up after bumping into a few problems.

I kept hearing good things about cppcheck in [articles and presentations by others](#references), though, so I finally decided it would be worth the trouble to get it working.

It turns out the problems were not that difficult to solve, given a combination of documentation and experimentation.  And the benefits were significant, so I'm quite happy to have added cppcheck to my tool box.

### Installing cppchceck
While cppcheck is available bundled with some distros, it's often an older version, so we're going to build and install it from source. As is more and more often the case, cppcheck has started using features of C++1x, so we're going to need a C++1x-capable compiler to build it.

If you're on an older distro (in my case, RH6) where the system compiler is not C++1x-capable, see my [earlier post](/blog/2015/01/02/building-clang/) about how to build clang (and/or gcc) to get a C++1x-capable compiler.  (Basically, it uses an older version of gcc to build a newer version, and the newer version to build clang).  

It took some trial-and-error to get the cppcheck build parameters right, but the [supplied build script](/pages/build_cppcheck.sh/index.html) should get the job done[^install].

    $ ./build_cppcheck.sh 2>&1 | tee build_cppcheck.out

[^install]: As usual, I prefer installing external packages in a non-standard location, so the build script is set up to do that.  See [this post](/blog/2015/01/02/building-clang/) for an explanation and rationale of this approach).

#### Verifying the installation
You'll need to add the cppcheck directory to your PATH (assuming the install location from the build script):

    $ export PATH=/build/share/cppcheck/1.73/bin:$PATH

If the build and install process worked, you should be able to invoke cppcheck from the command line, like so:

    $ cppcheck --version
    Cppcheck 1.73
 
If you see the message below instead, there's a problem with the RPATH setting:
   
    $ cppcheck --version
    cppcheck: /usr/lib64/libstdc++.so.6: version `GLIBCXX_3.4.15' not found (required by cppcheck)

The problem is typically either that the RPATH setting in the build is incorrect, or that the directory referenced by the RPATH setting does not exist.

### Running cppcheck

Now we're ready to run cppcheck, using the same approach we used with clang: 

    $ cd ${ITCBENCH_ROOT}  
    $ cc_driver.pl cppcheck.sh  2>&1 | 
    cppcheck2csv.pl -r ${ITCBENCH_ROOT} | 
    sort -u > cppcheck.csv

Note that instead of invoking cppcheck directly, we're invoking it via the [cppcheck.sh](/pages/cppcheck.sh/index.html) helper script, which supplies needed parameters to cppcheck.  It also creates an include file with the compiler's pre-defined macros, so those definitions will be visible to cppcheck.  This turns out to be particularly important with cppcheck, especially if the code you're trying to analyze uses `#ifdef`'s to control what code actually gets compiled (or seen by cppcheck)[^nosys].

[^nosys]: Note that cppcheck does not particularly like it when you include system include directories using `-I`.  Accordingly, we don't pass the `-s` switch to  cc_driver.pl when running cppcheck.

One of the settings in the helper script enables what cppcheck calls "inconclusive" results.  These are exactly what the name implies -- cppcheck isn't positive that the code is wrong, but it is at least suspicious.  Including these inconclusive results should tend to increase the number of false positives in theory, but in practice I haven't found false positives to be a big problem with either cppcheck or clang.  

### Analyzing the results
One of the first things you notice with cppcheck is that it includes more checks than clang.  Some of the additional warnings are for constructs that are not exactly *wrong*, but are either non-optimal, or indicators of potential problems.  For instance, cppcheck will warn when a variable is defined in a broader scope than is actually required ("scope ... can be reduced").  

<img class="center" src="/images/itcvscppcheck.png"> 

You can get a list of all the checks cppcheck is performing like so:

    $ cppcheck --doc 
    ...
    ## Other ##
    Other checks
    - division with zero
    - scoped object destroyed immediately after construction
    - assignment in an assert statement
    - free() or delete of an invalid memory location
    - bitwise operation with negative right operand
    - provide wrong dimensioned array to pipe() system command (--std=posix)


You can also generate a list of error ID's with this command:

    $ cppcheck --errorlist
    <error id="stringLiteralWrite" severity="error" msg="Modifying string literal directly or indirectly is undefined behaviour."/>
    <error id="sprintfOverlappingData" severity="error" msg="Undefined behavior: Variable &apos;varname&apos; is used as parameter and destination in s[n]printf()."/>
    <error id="strPlusChar" severity="error" msg="Unusual pointer arithmetic. A value of type &apos;char&apos; is added to a string literal."/>
    <error id="incorrectStringCompare" severity="style" msg="String literal &quot;Hello World&quot; doesn&apos;t match length argument for substr()."/>
    <error id="literalWithCharPtrCompare" severity="style" msg="String literal compared with variable &apos;foo&apos;. Did you intend to use strcmp() instead?"/>
    <error id="charLiteralWithCharPtrCompare" severity="style" msg="Char literal compared with pointer &apos;foo&apos;. Did you intend to dereference it?"/>
    <error id="incorrectStringBooleanError" severity="style" msg="Conversion of string literal &quot;Hello World&quot; to bool always evaluates to true."/>
 

You can suppress any errors you don't care to see by passing its id in the `--suppress=` flag.

## Comparing clang and cppcheck
There's a school of thought that says you should use as many compilers as possible to build your code, because each one will find different problems.  That's still a good idea, and even more so with static analysis tools.  

There's a certain amount of overlap between clang and cppcheck, but there are also significant differences.  In my experience, if clang reports something as a problem, it almost certainly is one, but clang also misses a lot of problems that it could detect.

<img class="center" src="/images/clangvscppcheck.png"> 

cppcheck can generate more warnings, and some of them are more stylistic issues, but it does detect certain classes of problems, like dead code and arithmetic over/underflow, that clang doesn't.

As I mentioned earlier, I haven't found false positives to be a major problem with either clang or cppcheck.

So, each tool has its place, and I like to use both.

# Conclusions
Static analysis tools can add real value to the software development process by detecting errors, especially errors in code that is never or almost never executed.

Commercial tools can be expensive (although still cheap compared to the money they save), and open-source tools can sometimes be hard to use (or at least hard to learn how to use).

The provided [helper scripts](/pages/REAME.md/index.html) ([repo here](https://github.com/btorpey/static)) should make it much easier to use these tools, and to keep track of warnings and compare the outputs of different tools by using a common format.

They can also be useful for before-and-after comparisions of different versions of a single codebase -- for example, as changes are being made to address issues detected by the tools.

# Acknowledgements
In addition to the people, projects and organizations mentioned earlier, the people at the NIST have been very helpful, and maintain an incredible collection of resources on the topic of static analysis for a number of languages, not just C++.  Some of those resources include the following, and are well worth checking out:

<https://samate.nist.gov/index.php/SAMATE_Publications.html>  
<https://samate.nist.gov/SARD/>  

If you've read any of my other posts, you may have noticed that the contents sidebar at the beginning of the article is a new thing.  Especially for longer-format articles, that TOC would seem to be very helpful.  Many thanks to [Robert Riemann](http://blog.riemann.cc/2013/04/10/table-of-contents-in-octopress/) for taking the trouble to explain how to do it.

I've been using the very nice [MacDown](http://macdown.uranusjr.com/) editor to create these posts -- thanks, Tzu-Ping!

# References
Some helpful references that I ran across while researching this article:

[Static Code Analysis, John Carmack](http://www.viva64.com/en/a/0087/)

[CppCon 2015: Jason Turner “The Current State of (free) Static Analysis"](https://youtu.be/sn1Vg8A_MPU)

[CppCon 2015: Neil MacIntosh “Static Analysis and C++: More Than Lint"](https://youtu.be/rKlHvAw1z50)

---

[^disclaimer]: Full disclaimer: I have not taken the time to review all of the ITC source to verify that the annotations are accurate and/or complete.  For the purpose of this exercise, we'll agree to assume that they are -- but if you'd like to suggest any improvements, I'm guessing the best place to do that would on the [repo](https://github.com/regehr/itc-benchmarks).

</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Static Analysis with clang]]></title>
    <link href="http://btorpey.github.io/blog/2015/04/27/static-analysis-with-clang/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-27T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://btorpey.github.io/blog/2015/04/27/static-analysis-with-clang</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/images/coil3.jpg" width="195" height="281">

I keep singing the praises of clang, and with good reason -- the [clang project](<http://clang.llvm.org/>) has been advancing the state of C/C++ compiler technology on Linux and OS X for quite a while now.  

The modular design of the compiler has also enabled the creation of a set of ancillary tools, including run-time "sanitizers" (which I [wrote about earlier](http://btorpey.github.io/blog/2014/03/27/using-clangs-address-sanitizer/)), as well as pretty-printers, and a tool to automatically upgrade code to C++11. 

Today I want to talk about clang's static analysis engine, which can do a deep-dive on your code and find problems that are hard for a human to detect, but that are amenable to a brute-force approach that models the run-time behavior of a piece of code, but at compile-time.

<!-- more -->

This is very different from dynamic analysis tools, like valgrind and clang's own sanitizers, which instrument the code at run-time to detect actual errors (e.g., reading uninitialized memory) that happen while the code is running.  With dynamic analysis, the only errors that can be detected are in code that is actually executed, so a latent bug that only manifests under unusual conditions[^heisenbug], can go un-detected.  By contrast, static analysis can potentially find bugs in code that is never (or almost never) actually executed.  

[^heisenbug]:  These are often called "Heisenbugs", in a nerd-humor pun on the [Heisenberg Uncertainty Principle](<http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uncertainty_principle>).

Sounds good, no?  Who wouldn't want to find bugs "automagically", without even needing to do any testing.  (Cause we all know how much programmers love testing ;-)

For example, running clang's static analyzer on some sample code turns up warnings similar to the following:

- Value stored to 'x' is never read
- The right operand of '!=' is a garbage value
- Potential leak of memory pointed to by 'x'
- Function call argument is an uninitialized value
- Use of memory after it is freed
- Called C++ object pointer is null

Some of the above warnings (e.g., value stored is never read) are most likely harmless, and just sloppy coding (perhaps because of copy-paste syndrome, about which I have more to say [here](http://btorpey.github.io/blog/2014/09/21/repent/)).  Others (e.g., called pointer is null), might be false positives, given the algorithms the analyzer uses[^falsepos].  Or, they could be real bugs that you just haven't hit yet, because the code is (almost) never executed.

[^falsepos]:  For instance, clang's analayzer attempts to figure out if a pointer can possibly be NULL by seeing if there is any code that checks for that condition.  If there is, then clang complains about any code that dereferences the pointer outside an `if (x != NULL)` block.  This algorithm isn't perfect, but it's about the best that can be done, especially since the analyzer only looks at a single file at a time.

Those are the really scary bugs, along with the ones where you can "get lucky" most of the time ... except when you don't.  The "garbage value" and "unitialized value" warnings fall into that category, and can be very hard to eyeball.  Again, dynamic analysis tools like valgrind can help find these bugs, but only if you hit that code in testing.

So, static analysis *is* good, but it's not magic.  Static analyzers can only find bugs that they are programmed to find, and they certainly don't find all bugs.  For instance, here's a bug that clang's static analysis doesn't find:

<div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='c++'><span class='line'><span class="kt">void</span> <span class="n">func</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="kt">char</span><span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">arg</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="kt">char</span> <span class="n">buf1</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="mi">10</span><span class="p">];</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="kt">char</span> <span class="n">buf2</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="mi">20</span><span class="p">];</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="n">strncpy</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">buf1</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">arg</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="k">sizeof</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">buf2</span><span class="p">));</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">}</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></notextile></div>

But the fact is that static analysis *will* find bugs, and it will find bugs that you most likely wouldn't find on your own, so it's a a good tool to have in your toolbox.  So, let's take a look at how to do that using clang.

The first step is to install clang.  If you're on OS X or Ubuntu, you should already have it, but if you're on RedHat this can be a bit tricky, so see [my previous post](http://btorpey.github.io/blog/2015/01/02/building-clang/) on how to get clang working.  (I've updated that post to add instructions for installing some of the static analysis tools that don't normally get installed with clang).

It turns out that there are three (3) different ways to run clang's static analyzer on your code, each with its own benefits and drawbacks.  We'll consider each of these in turn:

## Integrated with a typical build

If you use reasonably normal-looking makefiles to build your code, you can get static analysis going with a minimum of fuss.  If you're using cmake to create your makefiles, the same approach will work fine, so long as you're not overriding the values of CMAKE_C_COMPILER etc.  (And, as usual, if you're using autotools, [you're on your own;-)](https://twitter.com/timmartin2/status/23365017839599616).  

In this approach, you `export` some environment variables to invoke the analyzer instead of the compiler, like the following:

Variable|Value       |Meaning
--------|------------|-------
CC|ccc-analyzer|C compiler is redirected to clang analyzer (which in turn invokes the compiler, using the value of CCC_CC, below).
CXX|c++-analyzer|Similar to above, but for C++.
CCC_CC|clang|This environment variable is used by ccc-analyzer to invoke the actual C compiler.
CCC_CXX|clang++|ditto
LD|clang++|Specifies that the actual compiler should be used for linking.
CCC\_ANALYZER_VERBOSE|1|(Optional) Set this flag to get verbose output from the analyzer, including the list of errors checked.

<br>
With those variables set, you should just be able to invoke `make` to build your project, and Bob's your uncle.

One nice thing about this approach is that you get both compiler warnings and analyzer warnings together -- first, the analyzer invokes the compiler on the source file, and then performs the static analysis.

## Using the GUI tool

In a similar fashion as ccc-analyzer (above) front-ends make, you can use clang's [scan-build](http://clang-analyzer.llvm.org/scan-build.html) tool to front-end ccc-analyzer. In addition to invoking the compiler and analyzer, scan-build also collects the analyzer reports, including the control flow that the analyzer used to infer any errors, and presents that using a set of html pages that are written by default to the /tmp directory, and that look like this:

![](http://clang-analyzer.llvm.org/images/analyzer_html.png)

Personally, I find this fascinating.  Not only does the analyzer tell about what it thinks is a problem, but also *why* it thinks so.  

In the example above, you can see the steps that the analyzer follows to figure out that there is a problem with the code.  If you are wondering whether a particular warning is a false positive or not, this presentation can help you figure that out.  [^false2] It can also sometimes provide unexpected insights into the code that you might not come up with on your own.

To use this approach, you set your environment variables the same as described above, but instead of running make, you run `scan-build -V make`.  This will run your build and then launch a browser to view the results of the build.

### A small hitch...

Unfortunately, scan-build (and its scan-view companion) are not installed by default with clang.  I've updated the build script from my [earlier post](http://btorpey.github.io/blog/2015/01/02/building-clang/) on building clang on RedHat to install these files, but if you want to do it manually, run the following from the source tree you used to build and install clang:

<div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'><span class="c"># we need some addl bits that are not normally installed</span>
</span><span class='line'>cp -p  llvm/tools/clang/tools/scan-build/scan-build     <span class="k">$(</span>which clang<span class="k">)</span>/..
</span><span class='line'>cp -p  llvm/tools/clang/tools/scan-build/ccc-analyzer   <span class="k">$(</span>which clang<span class="k">)</span>/..
</span><span class='line'>cp -p  llvm/tools/clang/tools/scan-build/c++-analyzer   <span class="k">$(</span>which clang<span class="k">)</span>/..
</span><span class='line'>cp -p  llvm/tools/clang/tools/scan-build/sorttable.js   <span class="k">$(</span>which clang<span class="k">)</span>/..
</span><span class='line'>cp -p  llvm/tools/clang/tools/scan-build/scanview.css   <span class="k">$(</span>which clang<span class="k">)</span>/..
</span><span class='line'>cp -rp llvm/tools/clang/tools/scan-view/*               <span class="k">$(</span>which clang<span class="k">)</span>/..
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></notextile></div>
 
### Another small hitch...
In an [earlier post](http://btorpey.github.io/blog/2015/03/17/shadow/), I talked about how to use the `-isystem` flag to prevent selected headers from generating warnings.  Unfortunately, the [clang analyzer chokes on that flag](https://llvm.org/bugs/show_bug.cgi?id=13237#c9) -- so if you're using it, you will need to apply the patch below to successfully run the analyzer.  

<div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>svn diff ccc-analyzer
</span><span class='line'>Index: ccc-analyzer
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">===================================================================</span>
</span><span class='line'>--- ccc-analyzer	<span class="o">(</span>revision 234604<span class="o">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>+++ ccc-analyzer	<span class="o">(</span>working copy<span class="o">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>@@ -354,7 +354,8 @@
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="s1">&#39;-iprefix&#39;</span> <span class="o">=</span>&gt; 1,
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="s1">&#39;-iquote&#39;</span> <span class="o">=</span>&gt; 1,
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="s1">&#39;-iwithprefix&#39;</span> <span class="o">=</span>&gt; 1,
</span><span class='line'>-  <span class="s1">&#39;-iwithprefixbefore&#39;</span> <span class="o">=</span>&gt; 1
</span><span class='line'>+  <span class="s1">&#39;-iwithprefixbefore&#39;</span> <span class="o">=</span>&gt; 1,
</span><span class='line'>+  <span class="s1">&#39;-isystem&#39;</span> <span class="o">=</span>&gt; 1,
</span><span class='line'> <span class="o">)</span>;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'> my %LinkerOptionMap <span class="o">=</span> <span class="o">(</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></notextile></div>

[^false2]: At least in my experience, many of the warnings that appear at first to be false positives turn out to be real bugs, especially if you follow through the control flow the analyzer uses.

## Using a compilation database

Last but not least, you can also use a "compilation database" to invoke the static analyzer directly.  So, what is a compilation database, you ask?  This is a [simple format](http://clang.llvm.org/docs/JSONCompilationDatabase.html) introduced by clang that records the actual commands used to generate intermediate build products from source files, along with their parameters.

The analyzer needs this information to reproduce the environment used by the compiler, including pre-processor definitions and include file search paths.  

If you are using [cmake](http://cmake.org/) to drive your builds, creating a compilation database couldn't be easier -- simply add the `-DCMAKE_EXPORT_COMPILE_COMMANDS=ON` parameter to the cmake build command, or add the following to your main CMakeLists.txt file:

`set(CMAKE_EXPORT_COMPILE_COMMANDS ON)`

If you're not using cmake, you can still create a compilation database using plain old make by front-ending make with [Bear](<https://github.com/rizsotto/Bear>)[^bear], like so:

`bear make`

This will use Bear to drive the make process, leaving a `compile_commands.json` file in the current directory.

[^bear]: Building and installing Bear from source is relatively straightforward -- just keep in mind that you need python >= 2.7.

Once you've got the compilation database, invoking the analyzer can be done with a command like the following:

<div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'><span class="nb">export </span><span class="nv">COMPILE_DB</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="k">$(</span>/bin/pwd<span class="k">)</span>;
</span><span class='line'>grep file compile_commands.json |
</span><span class='line'>awk <span class="s1">&#39;{ print $2; }&#39;</span> |
</span><span class='line'>sed <span class="s1">&#39;s/\&quot;//g&#39;</span> |
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">while </span><span class="nb">read </span>FILE; <span class="k">do</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="o">(</span><span class="nb">cd</span> <span class="k">$(</span>dirname <span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">FILE</span><span class="k">})</span>;
</span><span class='line'>   clang-check -analyze -p <span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">COMPILE_DB</span><span class="k">}</span> <span class="k">$(</span>basename <span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">FILE</span><span class="k">})</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="o">)</span>;
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">done</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></notextile></div>

(There are simpler ways to invoke the analyzer, but the approach shown here will visit each source file in the same order that it was originally built, which can be handy).


## Conclusion
As we said earlier, static analysis is not magic, and it certainly won't find all your bugs.  But it will probably find some, and the ones it finds are likely to be nasty, so it's worth a certain amount of trouble.

Last but not least, this is by no means a complete explanation of clang's analyzer.  Like much of clang, the documentation lags the code, sometimes by a lot, so much of this information was obtained by trial-and-error, and/or by reading the code.  So, if you find something interesting, please [drop me a line](<mailto:wallstprog@gmail.com>), or leave a note in the comments section. 


## References

<http://clang.llvm.org/>

<http://clang-analyzer.llvm.org/index.html>

<http://clang.llvm.org/docs/ClangCheck.html>





</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Who Knows What Evil Lurks ...]]></title>
    <link href="http://btorpey.github.io/blog/2015/03/17/shadow/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-17T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://btorpey.github.io/blog/2015/03/17/shadow</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="/images/TheShadowComic01.jpg" width="222" height="333">

Pity the poor Shadow!  Even with the recent glut of super-heroes in movies, games and TV, the Shadow is nowhere to be seen.  

But I guess that's the whole point of being the Shadow.  

According to [this](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Shadow), the Shadow had "the mysterious power to cloud men's minds, so they could not see him".  Hmmm, that sounds like more than a few bugs I've known.

Read on to learn how to get your compiler to help you find and eliminate these "shadow bugs" from your code.

<!-- more -->

Recently I was cleaning up the code for one of our test programs, and I
suddenly started getting a crash at shutdown that I hadn’t seen before. The
stack trace looked more or less like I expected (except for the SEGV, of
course), and I spent several minutes staring at the code before the light bulb
came on.

As is often the case, once the light bulb did come on, my first reaction was
“Duh!”. It was a dumb mistake, but then I started to think: if it’s such a dumb
mistake, why didn’t the compiler warn me about it? Answering that question got
me looking into the state of compiler diagnostics, and taught me a few things I
hadn’t known (or had forgotten).

First, let’s take a look at the bug that was a bit of a head-scratcher, and that
prompted this post. I’ve distilled it down to just a few lines of code — take a
look and see if you can spot the bug:

<div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'><figcaption><span> (shadow.cpp)</span> <a href='/downloads/code/shadow/shadow.cpp'>download</a></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
<span class='line-number'>18</span>
<span class='line-number'>19</span>
<span class='line-number'>20</span>
<span class='line-number'>21</span>
<span class='line-number'>22</span>
<span class='line-number'>23</span>
<span class='line-number'>24</span>
<span class='line-number'>25</span>
<span class='line-number'>26</span>
<span class='line-number'>27</span>
<span class='line-number'>28</span>
<span class='line-number'>29</span>
<span class='line-number'>30</span>
<span class='line-number'>31</span>
<span class='line-number'>32</span>
<span class='line-number'>33</span>
<span class='line-number'>34</span>
<span class='line-number'>35</span>
<span class='line-number'>36</span>
<span class='line-number'>37</span>
<span class='line-number'>38</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='cpp'><span class='line'><span class="cp">#include &lt;memory&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">using</span> <span class="k">namespace</span> <span class="n">std</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">class</span> <span class="nc">D</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">public</span><span class="o">:</span>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="kt">void</span> <span class="n">Init</span><span class="p">()</span>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">};</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">class</span> <span class="nc">C</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">public</span><span class="o">:</span>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="n">C</span><span class="p">()</span>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="n">D</span><span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">_pD</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="k">new</span> <span class="n">D</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="n">_pD</span><span class="o">-&gt;</span><span class="n">Init</span><span class="p">();</span>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="o">~</span><span class="n">C</span><span class="p">()</span>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="k">delete</span> <span class="n">_pD</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">private</span><span class="o">:</span>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="n">D</span><span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">_pD</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">};</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="kt">int</span> <span class="n">main</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="kt">int</span> <span class="p">,</span> <span class="kt">char</span><span class="o">**</span> <span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="n">C</span> <span class="n">c</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="k">return</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">}</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></notextile></div>

The bug is in C's constructor, where instead of initializing the member variable (_pD), the
code instead creates a local variable with the same name. The local variable goes
out of scope on return and gets deleted (although the allocation
persists), but the member variable of the same name remains uninitialized. The
problem comes when we delete c, since C’s dtor deletes a pointer that is just a
bunch of random bits[^4]. The fix, of course, is to omit the type declaration on the
assignment, which causes the compiler to assign to the member variable, rather
than creating and then assigning to a local (stack) variable.

(I can already hear the howls of outrage at this code -- see [^1], [^2] and [^3] for a discussion if you're so inclined).

Granted that there are ways to avoid this problem by writing the code "correctly" (perfectly?) in the
first place. But still, if it’s such a dumb mistake, why didn’t the
compiler warn about it?

That was what puzzled me, especially since I thought our “diagnostic hygiene”
was pretty good. All our code is built with “-Wall -Wextra”, which is not quite
“everything but the kitchen sink”, but close.

But when we build with those flags, the compiler is perfectly happy:
<pre>
$ clang++ -g -Wall -Wextra shadow.cpp
$
</pre>

But running -- that's another story:
<pre>
$ ./a.out
*** glibc detected *** ./a.out: free(): invalid pointer: 0x0000000000400600 ***
...
Aborted (core dumped)
$ 
</pre>

When we load the core file into the debugger, we see that the offending instruction is the delete of _pD in C's destructor:

<pre>
$ gdb a.out core.897
(gdb) bt
#0  0x0000003a86032925 in raise () from /lib64/libc.so.6
#1  0x0000003a86034105 in abort () from /lib64/libc.so.6
#2  0x0000003a86070837 in __libc_message () from /lib64/libc.so.6
#3  0x0000003a86076166 in malloc_printerr () from /lib64/libc.so.6
#4  0x0000000000400720 in C::~C (this=0x7fffe6dbdec8) at shadow.cpp:23
#5  0x00000000004006a9 in main () at shadow.cpp:37
(gdb) 
</pre>

The result above is just one of three possible results. Let's take a look at each of these in turn:

1.  You may get no message at all - the code (appears to) work fine. 

	This is the result we get if we use gcc to compile the code.  With gcc, the allocation is (presumably) being satisfied by the operating system (e.g., by calling [sbrk](http://pubs.opengroup.org/onlinepubs/007908775/xsh/brk.html)).  Typically, the OS will zero-fill any memory that it allocates as a security precaution (see [here](http://stackoverflow.com/questions/8029584/why-does-malloc-initialize-the-values-to-0-in-gcc)  and [here](http://stackoverflow.com/questions/2688466/why-mallocmemset-is-slower-than-calloc) for details).  

	So, in this case, we're deleting a nullptr, and that is perfectly kosher [according to the standard](http://en.cppreference.com/w/c/memory/free). (Why that is may be a cause for debate, but it is).[^non-null]

[^non-null]:	Another possibility is that the bits are non-NULL, but the call to free doesn't immediately crash.  Instead, it may leave the data structures used to manage the heap in an inconsistent state, in such a way that it will cause a crash later.  This is the worst possible scenario, since this problem is almost impossible to debug.  In an upcoming column we're going to look at this situation in more detail, and talk about ways to avoid it.
	

2. You may get a message similar to  `*** glibc detected *** ./a.out: free(): invalid pointer` followed by a stack trace.  
 
	This happens when glibc can detect that the pointer being freed was not previously allocated.

	The memory management functions in glibc contain runtime checks to catch error conditions.  Some of these checks are enabled in all cases (because they are relatively inexpensive), while others must be specifically enabled.[^malloc-check]  In this particular case, the code in `free` is checking to see if the address being passed in has previously been allocated using e.g. `malloc`.  If not, the code signals an error.

	This is the result we get when using clang -- with clang, the  allocation request is being satisfied from memory that was previously allocated and freed, so the bits that make up the member variable _pD have already been scribbled on (i.e., they are non-zero), but glibc can tell the address is not one that was previously allocated.

3. You may get a message similar to `Segmentation fault (core dumped)`.  
	
	In our case, C's destructor is pretty minimal -- it just deletes the \_pD member variable.  In other cases, though, C's destructor may attempt to do more complicated processing before returning, and in those cases it's quite possible that that processing will trigger a crash on its own.  (For instance, if _pD is defined as a shared_ptr as opposed to a raw pointer, you would likely see a segmentation violation in the code that manipulates the shared_ptr).

# ... the Shadow Knows
This all could have been avoided if the compiler recongized that the declaration of _pD in C's constructor
hid the member variable, and with "-Wshadow" enabled in the compile, that is exactly what happens:

<pre>
﻿$ clang++ -Wall -Wextra -Wshadow shadow.cpp
shadow.cpp:17:10: warning: declaration shadows a field of 'C' [-Wshadow]
      D* _pD = new D;
         ^
shadow.cpp:27:7: note: previous declaration is here
   D* _pD;   
      ^
1 warning generated.
$
</pre>

gcc supports the flag also, although the message is slightly different
<pre>
$ g++ -Wall -Wextra -Wshadow shadow.cpp
shadow.cpp: In constructor ‘C::C()’:
shadow.cpp:17: warning: declaration of ‘_pD’ shadows a member of 'this'
$
</pre>

While both gcc and clang support the "-Wshadow" flag, the implementations are very different.  
gcc appears to strive for completeness, and in the process produces so many warnings as to render the use 
of "-Wshadow" pretty much useless.  That was certainly Linus’ opinion when
he wrote [this](<https://lkml.org/lkml/2006/11/28/239>), and it’s hard to
disagree.

The good news is that the clang developers have come up with a much
more useful implementation of "-Wshadow", which avoids a lot of the problems
Linus talks about.  For example, on one legacy-ish code base, gcc reports over 1100 shadow
warnings vs. just three for clang.  There's a terrific explanation  [here](<http://programmers.stackexchange.com/questions/122608/clang-warning-flags-for-objective-c-development/124574#124574>)
about how the clang team decides what category a particular diagnostic should belong to.

## Third-party Libraries

But, what if we use third-party libraries in our programs?  While clang does a very good job
of filtering out "false positive" shadow warnings, they can still crop up in some libraries, including Boost.  One
possible solution is to have wrapper includes that use #pragma's to suppress (or enable) certain warnings, prior to including
the real library headers.  That is in fact the approach suggested by the Boost maintainer when someone posted 
[a bug report](<https://svn.boost.org/trac/boost/ticket/9378#comment:15>) about 
the shadow warnings in Boost.  

But, that's tedious, error-prone, inconvenient and expensive.  Is there a better way?

It turns out that there is -- both gcc and clang provide the `-isystem` compiler flag to include header files, subject to 
[special rules](<https://gcc.gnu.org/onlinedocs/cpp/System-Headers.html>) that effectively eliminate warnings, 
even in macros that are expanded at compile-time.  

Note that if you're using cmake, the way to enable `-isystem` is to use the SYSTEM flag to include_directories, like so: 
`include_directories(SYSTEM ${Boost_INCLUDE_DIRS})`

## Fixing the code
There are three types of shadow warnings, each with a different cause and potential to cause trouble.  The different types are distinguished by what follows after the "warning: declaration shadows a" message:

|Type  | Explanation |
|------------- | -------------------------------------------- | 
| local variable | These are typically the least likely to be real problems, since local variables have limited lifetimes by defintion.  Even if these warnings don't indicate a genuine problem, it is best to eliminate them  by changing one or the other variable name, if only to prevent future confusion.
| field of "X" | As in the example above, these shadow warnings often point to a potential problem, given how easy it is to inadvertently include a type prefix in the statement meant to initialize the member variable, thereby declaring (and initializing) a new local variable instead.
| variable in the global namespace | This is perhaps the most dangerous of the three types, since accidentally introducing a new variable into scope can easily go unnoticed.  Everything appears to be working correctly, until at some point the newly introduced variable goes out of scope, exposing the un-initialized global variable.  

<br>

# Conclusion

I originally thought this would be a quick post about a somewhat obscure compiler warning -- maybe a 
"tidbit", but certainly nothing more than that.  But, as Tolkien said about "Lord of the Rings", "the tale grew in the telling".

Let's see what we've covered:

- What "-Wshadow" means, and why you might want to use it.
- How to selectively disable warnings, including "-Wshadow", for third-party libraries when
it creates more noise than value.
- How even seemingly trivial code can behave very differently when compiled with different compilers (e.g., gcc vs. clang).
- How to use value initialization to initialize even POD types to known (zero) values.

And that doesn't even include one of my original goals, which was to talk about compiler warnings
in general, and which ones you want to make sure you use in all your builds.  That will have to wait
for next time.

## TL;DR
- Enable "-Wshadow" in addition to whatever other compiler warnings you're using.  
  * Fix the warnings, even if they don't (appear to) matter.
- But only if you're using [clang](http://clang.llvm.org/)!
  * And if you're not using clang yet, it's time to start.
  * If you need help getting clang up and running on your system, be sure to check out [my earlier post](<http://btorpey.github.io/blog/2015/01/02/building-clang/>).



[^1]: The first point is that we should be initializing the member variable in the ctor, rather than assigning it, which would make this mistake impossible. That’s a valid point, mostly, but there are times when you can make a case for assignment being a simpler approach — for example, when you have multiple member variables, and when the order of assignment matters. Remember that member variables are initialized in the order of their declaration, not the order in which the initializers appear. Given that the order of declaration is often not obvious, it’s easy to see why one might prefer to use assignment to enforce the order of assignment in the body of the constructor.

[^2]: Another mostly valid point is that, if we are going to assign in the body of the ctor, we should at least initialize the members to some value before entering the constructor. The only defense to that is a misguided attempt to optimize out the initialization code, since we know we’re assigning to the member variable anyway. That’s arguably wrong, but not terribly so, and in any event is pretty common, at least in my experience. (OK, smarty-pants, do YOU always initialize ALL your member variables in EVERY constructor you write? Even if you're going to assign to them in the body of the constructor?  Really? Do you want your merit badge now, or at the jamboree?)

[^3]: Last but not least, we could use [value initialization](http://stackoverflow.com/a/2418195/203044) to ensure that even POD types in the class are [zero-initialized](http://en.cppreference.com/w/cpp/language/zero_initialization).

[^malloc-check]: We'll be discusing how to use glibc's error-checking in a future column.

[^4]: At least [according to the standard](http://en.cppreference.com/w/cpp/language/default_initialization).  Different implementations can, and do, behave differently. Or, as the old saying goes: "In theory, there is no difference between theory and practice.  In practice, there is".</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Building clang on RedHat]]></title>
    <link href="http://btorpey.github.io/blog/2015/01/02/building-clang/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-02T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://btorpey.github.io/blog/2015/01/02/building-clang</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/images/timallen.jpg" width="230" height="240" title="" >

clang is a great compiler, with a boatload of extremely helpful tools, including static analysis, run-time memory and data race analysis, and many others.  And it's apparently pretty easy to get those benefits on one of the supported platforms -- basically Ubuntu and Mac (via XCode).

That's fine, but if you get paid to write software, there's a good chance it's going to be deployed on RedHat, or one of its variants.  And, getting clang working on RedHat is a huge pain in the neck.  The good news is that I did the dirty work for you (ouch!), so you don't have to.
<!--more-->
<br>

Bootstrapping the compiler
--------------------------

Like almost all compilers, clang is written in a high-level language (in this case C++), so building clang requires a host compiler to do the actual compilation.  On Linux this is almost always gcc, since it is ubiquitous on Linux machines.  

There's a hitch, though -- as of version 3.3 some parts of clang are written in C++11, so the compiler used to compile clang needs to support the C++11 standard.

This is a real problem with RedHat, since the system compiler supplied with
RedHat 6 (the most recent version that is in wide use), is gcc 4.4.7.  That
compiler does not support C++11, and so is not able to compile clang.  So, the
first step is getting a C++11-compliant compiler so we can compile clang.  For
this example, we're going to choose gcc 4.8.2, for a variety of reasons[^5].  The
good news is that gcc 4.8.2 is written in C++ 98, so we can build it using the
system compiler (gcc 4.4.7).  

The next thing we have to decide is where to install gcc 4.8.2, and we basically have these choices:

-   We could install in /usr, where the new compiler would replace the system compiler.  Once we do that, though, we've effectively created a custom OS that will be required on all our development/QA/production machines going forward.  If "all our development/QA/production machines" == 1, this may not be a problem, but as the number increases things can get out of hand quickly. This approach also does not lend itself to being able to have more than one version of a particular package on a single machine, which is often helpful.

-   We could install in /usr/local (the default for gcc, and many other packages when built from source), so the new compiler would coexist with the system compiler.  The problem with this approach is that /usr/local can (and in practice often does) rapidly turn into a dumping-ground for miscellaneous executables and libraries.  Which wouldn't be so bad if we were diligent about keeping track of what they were and where they came from, but if we're going to do that we might as well ...

-   Install somewhere else -- it doesn't really matter where, as long as there's a convention. In this case, we're going to use the convention that any software that is not bundled with the OS gets installed in /build/share/\<package\>/\<version\>.  This approach makes it easy to know exactly what versions of what software we're running, since we need to specify its install directory explicitly in PATH and/or LD\_LIBRARY\_PATH.  It also makes it much easier to keep track of what everything is and where it came from.

Here's a script that will download gcc 4.8.2 along with its prerequisites, build it and install it as per the convention we just discussed:

<div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'><figcaption><span> (build-gcc.sh)</span> <a href='/downloads/code/clang/build-gcc.sh'>download</a></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
<span class='line-number'>18</span>
<span class='line-number'>19</span>
<span class='line-number'>20</span>
<span class='line-number'>21</span>
<span class='line-number'>22</span>
<span class='line-number'>23</span>
<span class='line-number'>24</span>
<span class='line-number'>25</span>
<span class='line-number'>26</span>
<span class='line-number'>27</span>
<span class='line-number'>28</span>
<span class='line-number'>29</span>
<span class='line-number'>30</span>
<span class='line-number'>31</span>
<span class='line-number'>32</span>
<span class='line-number'>33</span>
<span class='line-number'>34</span>
<span class='line-number'>35</span>
<span class='line-number'>36</span>
<span class='line-number'>37</span>
<span class='line-number'>38</span>
<span class='line-number'>39</span>
<span class='line-number'>40</span>
<span class='line-number'>41</span>
<span class='line-number'>42</span>
<span class='line-number'>43</span>
<span class='line-number'>44</span>
<span class='line-number'>45</span>
<span class='line-number'>46</span>
<span class='line-number'>47</span>
<span class='line-number'>48</span>
<span class='line-number'>49</span>
<span class='line-number'>50</span>
<span class='line-number'>51</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='sh'><span class='line'><span class="c">#!/bin/bash </span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nb">set</span> -exv
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="c">## modify the following as needed for your environment</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="c"># location where gcc should be installed</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">INSTALL_PREFIX</span><span class="o">=</span>/build/share/gcc/4.8.2
</span><span class='line'><span class="c"># number of cores</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">CPUS</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="k">$(</span>nproc<span class="k">)</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="c"># uncomment following to get verbose output from make</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="c">#VERBOSE=VERBOSE=1</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="c"># uncomment following if you need to sudo in order to do the install</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="c">#SUDO=sudo</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="c">## get everything</span>
</span><span class='line'>wget http://www.netgull.com/gcc/releases/gcc-4.8.2/gcc-4.8.2.tar.bz2
</span><span class='line'>wget https://gmplib.org/download/gmp/gmp-4.3.2.tar.bz2
</span><span class='line'>wget http://www.multiprecision.org/mpc/download/mpc-0.8.1.tar.gz
</span><span class='line'>wget http://www.mpfr.org/mpfr-2.4.2/mpfr-2.4.2.tar.bz2
</span><span class='line'>wget ftp://gcc.gnu.org/pub/gcc/infrastructure/cloog-0.18.1.tar.gz
</span><span class='line'>wget ftp://gcc.gnu.org/pub/gcc/infrastructure/isl-0.12.2.tar.bz2
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="c">## untar gcc</span>
</span><span class='line'>tar xf gcc-4.8.2.tar.bz2
</span><span class='line'><span class="c">## untar prereqs</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="c"># gmp</span>
</span><span class='line'>tar xf gmp-4.3.2.tar.bz2
</span><span class='line'>mv gmp-4.3.2 gcc-4.8.2/gmp
</span><span class='line'><span class="c"># mpc</span>
</span><span class='line'>tar xf mpc-0.8.1.tar.gz
</span><span class='line'>mv mpc-0.8.1 gcc-4.8.2/mpc
</span><span class='line'><span class="c"># mpfr</span>
</span><span class='line'>tar xf mpfr-2.4.2.tar.bz2
</span><span class='line'>mv mpfr-2.4.2 gcc-4.8.2/mpfr
</span><span class='line'><span class="c"># cloog</span>
</span><span class='line'>tar xf cloog-0.18.1.tar.gz
</span><span class='line'>mv cloog-0.18.1 gcc-4.8.2/cloog
</span><span class='line'><span class="c"># isl</span>
</span><span class='line'>tar xf isl-0.12.2.tar.bz2
</span><span class='line'>mv isl-0.12.2 gcc-4.8.2/isl
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="c"># build gcc</span>
</span><span class='line'>rm -rf gcc
</span><span class='line'>mkdir gcc
</span><span class='line'><span class="nb">cd </span>gcc
</span><span class='line'>../gcc-4.8.2/configure --prefix<span class="o">=</span><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">INSTALL_PREFIX</span><span class="k">}</span> --enable-languages<span class="o">=</span>c,c++ --disable-multilib
</span><span class='line'>make -j <span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">CPUS</span><span class="k">}</span> <span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">VERBOSE</span><span class="k">}</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="c"># install it</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">SUDO</span><span class="k">}</span> rm -rf <span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">INSTALL_PREFIX</span><span class="k">}</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">SUDO</span><span class="k">}</span> make install
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></notextile></div>

To run the script, change to an empty directory and then simply invoke the
script.  If you want to keep track of all the commands and output related to the
build, you can invoke the script using the trick I wrote about in an 
[earlier post](<http://btorpey.github.io/blog/2014/02/13/how-did-i-get-here/>).

Preparing to build
------------------

Now that we've built gcc, we can get started building clang[^1].  By default,
clang is built to use the C++ standard library (libstdc++) that is included with
gcc. That's the good news, since that means code generated using clang can be
intermixed freely with code generated with gcc -- which is almost all the code
on a typical Linux machine.

Finding the C++ standard library
--------------------------------

The libstdc++.so that is part of gcc is "versioned", which means that different library versions can have different symbols defined. Since we chose to install gcc 4.8.2 in a non-standard location, there are several settings that need to be tweaked to have code find and use that version of libstdc++[^4].

Let's start with a recap of how that works.

### Finding the C++ standard library at build-time

With a default installation of gcc, everything is easy: gcc itself is in /usr/bin, include files are in /usr/include (sort of), and library files are in /usr/lib and/or /usr/lib64. In cases where files are not installed in these locations, gcc itself keeps track of where it should look for dependencies, and the following command will show these locations:

    > g++ -E -x c++ - -v < /dev/null
    ...
    #include "..." search starts here:
    #include <...> search starts here:
     /usr/lib/gcc/x86_64-redhat-linux/4.4.7/../../../../include/c++/4.4.7
     /usr/lib/gcc/x86_64-redhat-linux/4.4.7/../../../../include/c++/4.4.7/x86_64-redhat-linux
     /usr/lib/gcc/x86_64-redhat-linux/4.4.7/../../../../include/c++/4.4.7/backward
     /usr/lib/gcc/x86_64-redhat-linux/4.4.7/include
     /usr/include
    End of search list.
    ...
    LIBRARY_PATH=/usr/lib/gcc/x86_64-redhat-linux/4.4.7/:/usr/lib/gcc/x86_64-redhat-linux/4.4.7/:/usr/lib/gcc/x86_64-redhat-linux/4.4.7/../../../../lib64/:/lib/../lib64/:/usr/lib/../lib64/:/usr/lib/gcc/x86_64-redhat-linux/4.4.7/../../../:/lib/:/usr/lib/

With our non-standard installation of gcc 4.8.2, the same command shows the values appropriate for that version of the compiler:

    > /build/share/gcc/4.8.2/bin/g++ -E -x c++ - -v < /dev/null
    ...
    #include "..." search starts here:
    #include <...> search starts here:
     /shared/build/share/gcc/4.8.2/bin/../lib/gcc/x86_64-unknown-linux-gnu/4.8.2/../../../../include/c++/4.8.2
     /shared/build/share/gcc/4.8.2/bin/../lib/gcc/x86_64-unknown-linux-gnu/4.8.2/../../../../include/c++/4.8.2/x86_64-unknown-linux-gnu
     /shared/build/share/gcc/4.8.2/bin/../lib/gcc/x86_64-unknown-linux-gnu/4.8.2/../../../../include/c++/4.8.2/backward
     /shared/build/share/gcc/4.8.2/bin/../lib/gcc/x86_64-unknown-linux-gnu/4.8.2/include
     /shared/build/share/gcc/4.8.2/bin/../lib/gcc/x86_64-unknown-linux-gnu/4.8.2/include-fixed
     /shared/build/share/gcc/4.8.2/bin/../lib/gcc/../../include
     /usr/include
    ...
    LIBRARY_PATH=/shared/build/share/gcc/4.8.2/bin/../lib/gcc/x86_64-unknown-linux-gnu/4.8.2/:/shared/build/share/gcc/4.8.2/bin/../lib/gcc/:/shared/build/share/gcc/4.8.2/bin/../lib/gcc/x86_64-unknown-linux-gnu/4.8.2/../../../../lib64/:/lib/../lib64/:/usr/lib/../lib64/:/shared/build/share/gcc/4.8.2/bin/../lib/gcc/x86_64-unknown-linux-gnu/4.8.2/../../../:/lib/:/usr/lib/

The situation with clang is a bit (!) more complicated. Not only does clang need
to be able to find its own include files and libraries, but it also needs to be
able to find the files for the compiler that clang is built with. In order
to successfully build clang with a non-standard compiler, we are going to need
to specify the following parameters to the clang build:

<table>
<col width="35%" />
<col width="60%" />
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td align="left"><p>CMAKE_C_COMPILER</p></td>
<td align="left"><p>The location of the C compiler to use.</p></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td align="left"><p>CMAKE_CXX_COMPILER</p></td>
<td align="left"><p>The location of the C++ compiler to use.</p></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td align="left"><p>CMAKE_INSTALL_PREFIX</p></td>
<td align="left"><p>The location where the compiler should be installed.</p></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td align="left"><p>CMAKE_CXX_LINK_FLAGS</p></td>
<td align="left"><p>Additional flags to be passed to the linker for C++ programs.  See below for more information.</p></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td align="left"><p>GCC_INSTALL_PREFIX</p></td>
<td align="left"><p>Setting this parameter when building clang is equivalent to specifying the <code>--gcc-toolchain</code> parameter when invoking clang. See below for more information.</p></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<br> 
While all these settings are documented in one place or another, as far as 
I know there is no single place that mentions them all.  (The clang developers apparently prefer writing code to writing
documentation ;-)  So, these settings have been cobbled together from a number
of sources (listed at the end of this article), and tested by much trial and
error.

The first three settings are plain-vanilla cmake settings, but the last two need some additional discussion:

### CMAKE\_CXX\_LINK\_FLAGS

In the clang build script this is set to `"-L${HOST_GCC}/lib64 -Wl,-rpath,${HOST_GCC}/lib64"`.  What this does is two-fold:

-   The `-L` parameter adds the following directory to the search path for the linker.  This is needed so the linker can locate the libraries installed with gcc 4.8.2.        

-   The `-Wl,-rpath,` parameter installs a ["run path"](<http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rpath>) into any executables (including shared libraries) created during the build.  This is needed so any executables created can find their dependent libraries at run-time. 

    Note that you can display the run path for any executable (including shared libraries) with the following command:

        > objdump -x /build/share/clang/trunk/bin/clang++ | grep RPATH
        RPATH                /build/share/gcc/4.8.2/lib64:$ORIGIN/../lib

### GCC\_INSTALL\_PREFIX

Unfortunately, by default, clang looks for include and library files in the standard system locations (e.g., /usr), regardless of what compiler was used to build clang. (I filed a [bug report](http://llvm.org/bugs/show_bug.cgi?id=20510) for this behavior, but the clang developers apparently feel this is reasonable behavior. Reasonable people may disagree ;-)

The work-around for this is to specify GCC\_INSTALL\_PREFIX when building clang -- this tells the clang build where the gcc that is being used to build clang is located. Among other things, this determines where the clang compiler will look for system include and library files at compile and link time.

Building clang
--------------

Now that we have that out of the way, we can build clang. The following script will download clang source from svn, build and install it.

<div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'><figcaption><span> (build-clang.sh)</span> <a href='/downloads/code/clang/build-clang.sh'>download</a></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
<span class='line-number'>18</span>
<span class='line-number'>19</span>
<span class='line-number'>20</span>
<span class='line-number'>21</span>
<span class='line-number'>22</span>
<span class='line-number'>23</span>
<span class='line-number'>24</span>
<span class='line-number'>25</span>
<span class='line-number'>26</span>
<span class='line-number'>27</span>
<span class='line-number'>28</span>
<span class='line-number'>29</span>
<span class='line-number'>30</span>
<span class='line-number'>31</span>
<span class='line-number'>32</span>
<span class='line-number'>33</span>
<span class='line-number'>34</span>
<span class='line-number'>35</span>
<span class='line-number'>36</span>
<span class='line-number'>37</span>
<span class='line-number'>38</span>
<span class='line-number'>39</span>
<span class='line-number'>40</span>
<span class='line-number'>41</span>
<span class='line-number'>42</span>
<span class='line-number'>43</span>
<span class='line-number'>44</span>
<span class='line-number'>45</span>
<span class='line-number'>46</span>
<span class='line-number'>47</span>
<span class='line-number'>48</span>
<span class='line-number'>49</span>
<span class='line-number'>50</span>
<span class='line-number'>51</span>
<span class='line-number'>52</span>
<span class='line-number'>53</span>
<span class='line-number'>54</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='sh'><span class='line'><span class="c">#!/bin/bash</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nb">set</span> -exv
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="c">## modify the following as needed for your environment</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="c"># location where clang should be installed</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">INSTALL_PREFIX</span><span class="o">=</span>/build/share/clang/trunk
</span><span class='line'><span class="c"># location of gcc used to build clang</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">HOST_GCC</span><span class="o">=</span>/build/share/gcc/4.8.2
</span><span class='line'><span class="c"># number of cores</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">CPUS</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="k">$(</span>nproc<span class="k">)</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="c"># uncomment following to get verbose output from make</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="c">#VERBOSE=VERBOSE=1</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="c"># uncomment following if you need to sudo in order to do the install</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="c">#SUDO=sudo</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="c">#</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="c"># gets clang tree from svn into ./llvm</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="c"># params (e.g., -r) can be specified on command line</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="c">#</span>
</span><span class='line'>rm -rf llvm
</span><span class='line'><span class="c">## get everything</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="c"># llvm</span>
</span><span class='line'>svn co <span class="nv">$*</span> http://llvm.org/svn/llvm-project/llvm/trunk llvm
</span><span class='line'><span class="c"># clang</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nb">cd </span>llvm/tools
</span><span class='line'>svn co <span class="nv">$*</span> http://llvm.org/svn/llvm-project/cfe/trunk clang
</span><span class='line'><span class="nb">cd</span> -
</span><span class='line'><span class="c"># extra</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nb">cd </span>llvm/tools/clang/tools
</span><span class='line'>svn co <span class="nv">$*</span> http://llvm.org/svn/llvm-project/clang-tools-extra/trunk extra
</span><span class='line'><span class="nb">cd</span> -
</span><span class='line'><span class="c"># compiler-rt</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nb">cd </span>llvm/projects
</span><span class='line'>svn co <span class="nv">$*</span> http://llvm.org/svn/llvm-project/compiler-rt/trunk compiler-rt
</span><span class='line'><span class="nb">cd</span> -
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="c">## build clang w/gcc installed in non-standard location</span>
</span><span class='line'>rm -rf clang
</span><span class='line'>mkdir -p clang
</span><span class='line'><span class="nb">cd </span>clang
</span><span class='line'>cmake -DCMAKE_C_COMPILER<span class="o">=</span><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">HOST_GCC</span><span class="k">}</span>/bin/gcc -DCMAKE_CXX_COMPILER<span class="o">=</span><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">HOST_GCC</span><span class="k">}</span>/bin/g++ -DGCC_INSTALL_PREFIX<span class="o">=</span><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">HOST_GCC</span><span class="k">}</span> -DCMAKE_CXX_LINK_FLAGS<span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">&quot;-L${HOST_GCC}/lib64 -Wl,-rpath,${HOST_GCC}/lib64&quot;</span> -DCMAKE_INSTALL_PREFIX<span class="o">=</span><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">INSTALL_PREFIX</span><span class="k">}</span> -DLLVM_ENABLE_ASSERTIONS<span class="o">=</span>ON -DCMAKE_BUILD_TYPE<span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">&quot;Release&quot;</span> -DLLVM_TARGETS_TO_BUILD<span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">&quot;X86&quot;</span> ../llvm
</span><span class='line'>make -j <span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">CPUS</span><span class="k">}</span> <span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">VERBOSE</span><span class="k">}</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="c"># install it</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">SUDO</span><span class="k">}</span> rm -rf <span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">INSTALL_PREFIX</span><span class="k">}</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">SUDO</span><span class="k">}</span> make install
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="c"># we need some addl bits that are not normally installed</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">SUDO</span><span class="k">}</span> cp -p ../llvm/tools/clang/tools/scan-build/scan-build  <span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">INSTALL_PREFIX</span><span class="k">}</span>/bin
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">SUDO</span><span class="k">}</span> cp -p ../llvm/tools/clang/tools/scan-build/ccc-analyzer  <span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">INSTALL_PREFIX</span><span class="k">}</span>/bin
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">SUDO</span><span class="k">}</span> cp -p ../llvm/tools/clang/tools/scan-build/c++-analyzer  <span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">INSTALL_PREFIX</span><span class="k">}</span>/bin
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">SUDO</span><span class="k">}</span> cp -p ../llvm/tools/clang/tools/scan-build/sorttable.js  <span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">INSTALL_PREFIX</span><span class="k">}</span>/bin
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">SUDO</span><span class="k">}</span> cp -p ../llvm/tools/clang/tools/scan-build/scanview.css <span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">INSTALL_PREFIX</span><span class="k">}</span>/bin
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">SUDO</span><span class="k">}</span> cp -rp ../llvm/tools/clang/tools/scan-view/*  <span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">INSTALL_PREFIX</span><span class="k">}</span>/bin
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></notextile></div>

Note that you can specify a parameter to the script (e.g., `-r 224019`) to get a specific version of clang from svn.


> Since this article was originally published, there have been some changes to the prerequisites for building clang:
> you will need cmake 2.8.12.2 or later, and python 2.7 or later. 


Building using clang
--------------------

At this point, we should have a working clang compiler that we can use to build and run our own code. But once again, because the "host" gcc (and libstdc++) are installed in a non-standard location, we need to tweak a couple of build settings to get a successful build.

### Specifying the compiler to use

There are a bunch of ways to specify the compiler, depending on what build system you're using -- I'll mention a couple of them here.

If you're using make, you can prefix the make command as follows:

    CC=clang CXX=clang++ make ... 

If you're using cmake you can [specify the compiler to use](http://www.cmake.org/Wiki/CMake_FAQ#How_do_I_use_a_different_compiler.3F) on the cmake command line, as follows:

    cmake -DCMAKE_C_COMPILER=clang -DCMAKE_CXX_COMPILER=clang++ ... 

Personally, I find that ridiculously inconvenient, so in my CMakeLists.txt file I specify the compiler directly:

    # cmake doc says this is naughty, but their suggestions are even worse...
    if("$ENV{COMPILER}" STREQUAL "gcc")
      set(CMAKE_C_COMPILER      gcc)
      set(CMAKE_CXX_COMPILER    g++)
    elseif("$ENV{COMPILER}" STREQUAL "clang")
      set(CMAKE_C_COMPILER      clang)
      set(CMAKE_CXX_COMPILER    clang++)
    endif()

In any of the above, you can either specify the full path to the compiler, or just specify the name of the compiler executable (as above), and make sure that the executable is on your PATH.

Last but not least, if you're using GNU autotools -- you're on your own, good luck! The only thing I want to say about autotools is that [I agree with this guy](https://twitter.com/timmartin2/status/23365017839599616).

### Finding the C++ standard library at run-time

Any code genrated using clang is also going to need to be able to find the libraries that clang was built with at run-time. There are a couple of ways of doing that:

-   Similar to what we did above when building clang, you can specify the `-Wl,-rpath,` parameter to the linker to set a run path for your executables.
     Note that if you're using cmake, it will [automatically strip the rpath](<http://www.cmake.org/Wiki/CMake_RPATH_handling>) from all files when running `make install`, so you may need to disable that by setting `CMAKE_SKIP_INSTALL_RPATH` to false in your build.

-   Alternatively, you will need to make sure that the proper library directory is on your `LD_LIBRARY_PATH` at run-time[^3].

##So, What Could Possibly Go Wrong?

If you've followed the directions above, you should be good to go, but be warned that, just like in "Harry Potter", messing up any part of the spell can cause things to go spectacularly wrong. Here are a few examples:

-   If you try to use the system compiler (gcc 4.4.7) to build clang, you'll get an error like the following:

<!-- -->

    CMake Error at cmake/modules/HandleLLVMOptions.cmake:17 (message):
      Host GCC version must be at least 4.7!

-   The clang build executes code, that was built with clang, as part of the build step. If clang can't find the correct (i.e., gcc 4.8.2) version of libstdc++ at build time, you will see an error similar to the following:

<!-- -->

    Linking CXX static library ../../../../lib/libclangAnalysis.a
    [ 51%] Built target clangAnalysis
    [ 51%] Building CXX object tools/clang/lib/Sema/CMakeFiles/clangSema.dir/SemaConsumer.cpp.o
    [ 51%] Building CXX object tools/clang/lib/ARCMigrate/CMakeFiles/clangARCMigrate.dir/TransAutoreleasePool.cpp.o
    [ 51%] Building CXX object tools/clang/lib/AST/CMakeFiles/clangAST.dir/ExprConstant.cpp.o
    Scanning dependencies of target ClangDriverOptions
    [ 51%] Building Options.inc...
    ../../../../../bin/llvm-tblgen: /usr/lib64/libstdc++.so.6: version `GLIBCXX_3.4.15' not found (required by ../../../../../bin/llvm-tblgen)

-   If you build clang without specifying the `-Wl,-rpath` parameter, clang won't be able to find the libraries it needs at compile-time:

<!-- -->

    > clang++ $* hello.cpp && ./a.out
    clang++: /usr/lib64/libstdc++.so.6: version `GLIBCXX_3.4.14' not found (required by clang++)
    clang++: /usr/lib64/libstdc++.so.6: version `GLIBCXX_3.4.18' not found (required by clang++)
    clang++: /usr/lib64/libstdc++.so.6: version `GLIBCXX_3.4.15' not found (required by clang++)

-   If the GCC\_INSTALL\_PREFIX setting isn't specified when you build with clang, it will look for system files in /usr, rather than the proper directory, and you will see something like this:

<!-- -->

    > clang++ $* hello.cpp && ./a.out
    In file included from hello.cpp:1:
    In file included from /usr/lib/gcc/x86_64-redhat-linux/4.4.7/../../../../include/c++/4.4.7/iostream:40:
    In file included from /usr/lib/gcc/x86_64-redhat-linux/4.4.7/../../../../include/c++/4.4.7/ostream:40:
    In file included from /usr/lib/gcc/x86_64-redhat-linux/4.4.7/../../../../include/c++/4.4.7/ios:40:
    In file included from /usr/lib/gcc/x86_64-redhat-linux/4.4.7/../../../../include/c++/4.4.7/exception:148:
    /usr/lib/gcc/x86_64-redhat-linux/4.4.7/../../../../include/c++/4.4.7/exception_ptr.h:143:13: error: unknown type name 'type_info'
          const type_info*
                ^
    1 error generated.

I've probably missed a couple, but you get the idea.

Conclusion
----------

There may be another way to build clang successfully on a RH-based system, but
if there is I've yet to discover it. As mentioned earlier, bits and pieces of
this information have been found in other sources, including the following:

<http://llvm.org/docs/GettingStarted.html#getting-a-modern-host-c-toolchain>

<http://clang-developers.42468.n3.nabble.com/getting-clang-to-find-non-default-libstdc-td3945163.html>

<https://github.com/google/sanitizers/wiki/MemorySanitizerBuildingClangOnOlderSystems>

<http://llvm.org/docs/CMake.html>
 

[^1]: You will need at least version 2.8.12.2 of cmake to do the build, which is not native on RH/CentOS 6.  That version can be installed using "Add/Remove Software" or yum.  (Or, of course, you can build it from source). You will also need python 2.7 or later, which is probably better built from source, since the RH repos apparently use the non-standard name "python27" for the executable.

[^3]: This is the approach we use in my shop -- we have a hard-and-fast rule that application code cannot contain a run path, and we deliberately strip any existing RPATH entries from code that is being deployed to QA and production as a security measure.

[^4]: I may go into more detail on this in a later post, but in the meantime if you're interested you should consult Ulrich Drepper's "How to Write Shared Libraries" at <http://www.akkadia.org/drepper/dsohowto.pdf>.

[^5]: One reason is that gcc 4.9.0 can't compile libc++, the llvm version of the C++ standard library -- see <http://lists.llvm.org/pipermail/cfe-dev/2014-April/036650.html> for more detail.  While we're not going to discuss using libc++ in this post, we may get into that later on.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
