<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: mgmt | Confessions of a Wall Street Programmer]]></title>
  <link href="http://btorpey.github.io/blog/categories/mgmt/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://btorpey.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-01-24T10:46:04-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://btorpey.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bill Torpey]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Status Meetings]]></title>
    <link href="http://btorpey.github.io/blog/2014/08/21/status-reports/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-21T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://btorpey.github.io/blog/2014/08/21/status-reports</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="/images/the-office-boring-meeting1.jpg" width="262" height="211"> 

One of the banes of corporate life is the status meeting.  It would be nice to get rid of them, but then it would be nice to 
get rid of all the lawyers too[^1], and I don't see that happening either.  

So, how do we make them better?
Well, for starters we could make them shorter.  Here's a way to do that.  

<!--more-->

I've had two really good managers in my career (although I have no idea whether
that means I've been blessed or cursed ;-) I learned different things from each of my managers -- some of them pragmatic and
some more in the "touchy-feely" category. This one is purely pragmatic (which
is not to say that is all I learned from him, but those stories are for another day).

My manager (I'll call him Mike, because that's his name) set up this structure
for a trading system project I was working on under his direction. We would have
a status meeting on Monday mornings, which would set the agenda for the coming
week, and with the following structure in place that meeting would typically take no more
than 30 minutes. At the end, everybody knew what they needed to do, and we all
got to work with a clear purpose.

In preparation for this meeting, each person would create a status report, which consisted of the following categories, no more
and no less:

### Planned and Accomplished

This is where you list the tasks that you planned to get done during the
period, and that were actually completed. And, by completed we're not talking
about 90% -- once a task gets into this category, you don't expect to see it
again -- if you do, then it wasn't really complete in the first place.

This sort of implies that tasks can be accomplished in one iteration, and so naturally
forces you to think in terms of discrete quanta of accomplishment.  To paraphrase Woody Allen,
"A project is like a shark.  It has to constantly move forward or it dies".  

### Unplanned and Accomplished

Of course, in the real world things never go as smoothly as they are supposed
to. (Another way of saying this is: "In theory there is no difference between
theory and practice. In practice there is.") So, this is where you list those
items that came up "out of the blue", but which you had to deal with. An example
might be production problems, customer engagements, or other things that are
unpredictable.

### Planned and Not Accomplished

You would like this category to be empty much of the time, but that doesn't
always happen. Certain tasks may have dependencies on external agents over which
you have no control, for instance -- so even if you're the world's best planner,
you're going to get tasks in here from time to time. Typically you would also
include a brief explanation of why something didn't happen that was supposed to,
which might feed into the "Issues for Management Attention" section later.

### Planned for Next Period

This is where you list the tasks that you intend to complete during the next
iteration. Some may be new, and if there's anything in the "Planned and Not
Accomplished" section, those would generally show up here as well until they are
completed. Similarly, everything that appears here will end up in either
"Planned and Accomplished" or "Planned and Not Accomplished" next time.

### Issues for Management Attention

Here's where you discuss any "blockers" that are preventing you from
accomplishing your goals. In many cases, this will include dependencies on
external entities, and these provide an opportunity for your manager to exercise his
or her persuasive powers on other parts of the organization.

And that's it -- just five categories, with a real focus on what's truly important.

After learning this technique, I've used it with great success in all sorts of
situations, and have also passed it along to others, who have all been quite happy with it. 
It strikes just the right balance between too much and too little
information, and also focuses the information in a way that is most useful.

On Mike's project, we had these meetings on Monday mornings, but Friday also
works -- that way you get it out of the way and come into the new week rarin' to
go.

If you're a manager, give this a try and see if it doesn't streamline one of
your more onerous tasks. If you're not a manager, then you probably have one,
and you can suggest using this for your status reports. Or, you can just use
this template to help you focus yourself on what you need to be doing.

[^1]:  Actually, some of my best friends are lawyers, so this doesn't apply to them ;-)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
